good evening everyone i'll now call to order this september 23rd meeting of lancaster city council a few reminders at the top of our meeting this meeting and its participants are being recorded this evening please take a moment to silence your phones and devices if you haven't done so already one note on the agenda bill six that was scheduled for first reading this evening will not be discussed it will has been moved to the first meeting in october during this meeting there will be opportunities for public comment the first general public comment period is open for residents who registered in advance of the meeting to speak about items that are not on the agenda residents may also comment on individual items on our agenda in the legislative section which is section 9. finally a second public comment period will be at the end of this meeting for any other speakers wishing to address council for all speakers no no matter in which portion of the agenda. Please begin with your name and block of residence for our meeting record. Be advised that public comment is not necessarily a question and answer period. All comments are limited to three minutes per speaker, and to keep time, I have this light in front of me. It will turn green when a speaker begins. It will turn yellow, it will blink yellow when there is one minute remaining, and blink red when three minutes has been exhausted. I appreciate everyone's cooperation in advance ensuring that we all have equal time uh last but not least speakers addressing city council and the members of this audience will be expected to conduct themselves in an orderly manner and remain respectful to others thank you now for all of those who are willing and able please rise
for the pledge of allegiance mr harris would you please call the role of members yes madam president
Mr. Menn here Mr. Arroyo here Mr. Cleese here Ms. Craig here Ms. Diaz here Mr. Hirsch
and President Beke here Councillor Hirsch is excused this evening we'll now move to the approval of the minutes of the September 9th meeting of City Council motion to approve second we have a motion and a second for our meeting
minutes councillors any comments on them hearing none Mr. Harris Mr. Menn aye Mr. Arroyo aye Aye. Mr. Felice? Aye. Ms. Craig? Aye. Ms. Diaz?
Aye. And President Becker? Aye. We'll now move to proclamations, honors, awards, and resolutions of recognition, of which we have one this evening. Is that right, Mr. Harris? Yes, Madam President, we do.
We have the Governor's Hispanic Heritage Month Proclamation. Thank you very much.
Councillors, this evening we're joined by Jose A. Nunez Ruiz, who is a commissioner lancaster county on the governor's advisory commission on latino affairs he's wanted to come here this evening to read us the proclamation signed by governor shapiro recognizing hispanic heritage month if you would like to come forward jose thank you so much for being here i know that you may have some words that you would like to share and then you'll be reading the content of the resolution in spanish for us this evening you got it good
Good evening to all, to City Council, to Mayor Soares, and to the public today. I'm a proud resident of the city of Lancaster. I live on the 100 block of South Queen Street, so I'm very proud to be part of this. I consider myself an Amatrican and also be proud to represent our county in the Governor's Advisory Commission on Latino Affairs. So today I bring you, like I said, the proclamation on behalf of our governor, the Honorable Josh Shapiro, And our executive director, Olga Negron, who is the director of the commission. And the proclamation reads as follows. I will be doing the proclamation in Spanish. Hope you. Thank you.
Proclamation for the governor. Por lo cuanto, en vez de la herencia hispana, es una oportunidad para celebrar las ricas tradiciones culturales y honrar las contribuciones y los logros significativamente de nuestra comunidad hispana y latinoamericana en medicina, leyes, negocio, tecnología, compromiso civil, gobierno y cultura. Y por lo cuanto, los latinoamericanos son el grupo minatorio ético más grande en los Estados Unidos, con 68 millones y la comunidad minoritaria más creciente rápidamente en Pennsylvania con 1.2 millones y por lo cuanto los latinos americanos han servido con distinción en los conflictos militares desde la regla de la revolución y continúa a defender nuestro país hoy en día como miembros de las Fuerzas Armadas. Estos hombres y mujeres valientes nos dan honor y estamos agradecidos por su servicio y sacrificio. Y por lo cuanto, la dedicación de los hispanos y latinoamericanos en las comunidades es una parte integral de Pennsylvania. Han hecho contribuciones en nuestra sociedad diversa a compartir su cultura y talento. Y por lo cuanto, no importa cómo se vea, de dónde venga, a quién ame y ni a quién rece, usted tiene un lugar en Pennsylvania y este estado engullece en un rey las historias y las contribuciones de los hispanos y latinoamericanos en nuestro estado y en toda la nación. Por lo tanto, yo, Josh Shapiro, gobernador de Pennsylvania, proclamo por el presente el 15 de septiembre hasta el 15 de octubre de 2025 como el mes de la herencia hispanidad. El reconocimiento a los hispanos y latinoamericanos pasado y presente en nuestro estado. Animo a todos los residentes de Pennsylvania a celebrar esta importante observancia.
That is a message from our governor in the second spoken language, which is Spanish, in our commonwealth. So I want to thank you for the opportunity for letting me read this, especially since this is my first time reading it in Spanish. but my second time reading in Spanish for my first time reading here in Spanish so thank you very much and like I said let's not forget that Latinos and Hispanos and Latino Americanos are always, we're growing 1.2 million and that growth will continue in Lancaster County, so many Latino leaders have come from here so I am proud to be a Puerto Rican, I am proud to be Alakansian and like I always say when I travel throughout the state anywhere. I'm a proud Amish Rican. So, thank you for the opportunity, and feliz mes de la Hispanidad.
Thank you. I appreciate you being here this evening, Jose. We, as you may recall, counselors and members of the public, passed our resolution honoring Hispanic Heritage Month at our last meeting, and I will mention that we are having a celebration for Hispanic Heritage Month on october 4th in yule plaza from 2 to 8 p.m featuring dancers entertainers award ceremony food and drink vendors and so much fun so please come out and join us to celebrate that in the city before you uh you go away from from your seat there counselors do you have any additional comments uh questions uh for jose thank you for being here so much on this rainy evening that will take us to our first public comment period and thank you for leaving that with the city clerk this comment period again is reserved for residents who have contacted the city clerk prior to this meeting to request the opportunity to address City Council mr. Harris do we have any commenters for this first period we do not thank you very much we will then move to our next item on the agenda which is reports requested by council confirming that we
have none of those this evening I apologize I was I was incorrect so this
evening we do have a report requested by council because of the new timeline set forth in our new charter we can say new until the end of this year and then it's not new anymore I guess we will be receiving our mayor's budget address
this evening mayor sirachi uh thank you council president um would you mind taking one it is september 23rd and i'm introducing the 2026 budget this may be the earliest that any mayor in recent history has introduced a budget and it is one of the many changes brought by the adoption of the home rule charter last year approved by 68 of the voters of lancaster the home rule charter has institutionalized a set of best management practices that really define my administration's strategic priority of sound government with home rule council and the public not only have a budget introduced earlier than before but also a comprehensive capital plan encompassing the general fund and each of the utilities council has been engaged in a review of the capital plan for several months and will be voting on the capital plan later this evening in addition a new controller with additional responsibilities and input into the city's accounting practices financial policies and budgeting will be elected on november 4th alongside a new mayor and council majority plus the administrative code under review by council now contemplates a set of financial policies including an official fund balance policy investment policy and debt policy further institutionalizing best practices perhaps most notably the home rule charter allows us to move away from a cycle of regular property tax increases by adjusting the earned income tax this was done last year and as a result we are projecting an 11 increase in earned income tax revenues in 2026. finally relative to this budget message the home rule charter also lays out what my message should include so let's get those portions out of the way in the 2026 general fund we are projecting 81.8 million in revenues and 81.7 million in expenses no property tax or earned income tax increase is proposed i'm going to say that again you guys let's cause for celebration no property tax or earned income tax increase is proposed on the revenue side overall income is projected to rise just two percent which is actually a bit higher than we anticipated given that this is the first budget without american rescue plan fund rescue plan act funds there are a couple of other bright spots including increases in investment earnings and permit fees which i'll come back to on the expense side there is a projected increase of six percent which is two percent higher than our goal of four percent due to a variety of factors including health insurance up five percent and staffing including the restoration of a chief of staff position for the incoming administration the filling of vacant positions and the addition of a few new positions additionally we have been making adjustments to salary allocations between the general fund and utilities as you are aware we have positions whose job responsibilities are split between the general fund and utilities approximately 36 360 000 has been moved from various utilities back to the general fund primarily impacting the department of public works within the enterprise funds there are no proposed increases in trash and recycling storm water sewer or water for inside customers pretty good however next week we are filing a rate case before the public utility commission to raise water rates for outside city customers we expect let me just say again those are outside city customers we're going to the puc we expect these rates to go into effect into mid-2026 i also want to highlight our general fund reserve in 2025 we projected adding 2.4 million dollars to the general reserve fund however because of increases in earned income tax and permitting revenues not including the 7.8 million in building permit revenues related to the carissa project we anticipate this year with 4.7 million in addition additional revenue we are requesting that 1 million be allocated to the 2026 budget this still provides a fund balance contribution of 3.7 million and will increase our fund balance percent from 17 to 22 which is aligned with the proposed fund balance policy that is in the administrative code presently being contemplated by council the 7.8 million dollars generated from the carissa project a 260 greenfield road is a total outlier in consultation with our auditor this will be treated similar to a grant meaning it is not showing in the revenues or expenses related to the budget a separate report will be provided to council outlining that revenue and all the expenses that are related to the data center council will have some decisions to make related to the utilization of utilization of these funds for which i will be preparing a separate memo for your consideration number two there are no significant changes to the work of the city included in this budget however i do want to call your attention to one area of our operations that you will be hearing more about during the department budget presentations and that is permitting on average the city receives approximately 3 000 permits annually 80 of which are building permits permitting is a complicated government function with multiple city departments providing review and has been a source of ongoing frustration both internally and externally we've been listening and as i reported to council last month we have been making progress and there is much more work to do to make it faster clearer and fully online this budget proposes additional investments in centralizing the permitting within administrative services since nearly every department has a permitting role you'll hear more details in the department budget presentations i want to emphasize that while this area requires additional improvements we are offsetting added costs by being more strategic about what kind of work is outsourced in turn this is generating the additional revenue to support those costs number three while we usually only discuss the city's debt position when we are soliciting a bond this is a good moment to note progress earlier in my tenure the city's credit outlook had been downgraded by moody's to a negative outlook then neutral and now we are positive in large measure because we demonstrated our willingness to strengthen our financial position by moving to home rule and increasing our earned income tax number four additional information regarding the budget will be presented at the october 6 council committee meeting along with a detailed line item budget followed by two rounds of department budget presentations the first set of department budget presentations will be on tuesday october 21st and the second will be on tuesday november the 18th these sessions replace the all-day saturday session traditionally held in december and finally as i prepared this this budget address my last one i revisited mayor gray's final budget message delivered in 2017 he noted that over his 12 years a priority was restoring the city's fiscal stability through practices that his administration put in place a 69 million dollar deficit by 2012 was averted over the last eight years we have built on this foundation and i'm pleased to say that with the passage of home rule we have eliminated our structural deficit it is a really big deal however continued fiscal restraint and a continued strong economy are both necessary for the city's long-term financial health a downturn in either will have consequences which is why i urge future administrations and councils to continue holding the line on spending and tax increases finally i want to thank the staff who have been working on the budget for months especially the accounting team under director campbell's leadership thank you tina this has been this is truly a team effort and has been one of the smoothest budget processes especially given that is being delivered months earlier i look forward to continued conversation in the months ahead and thank you council for the opportunity to present my final did i say final enough budget message thank you very much mayor sirachi council looks forward to receiving
the budget on october 6 and hearing our initial presentation at that meeting of committees of council i'll also note that generally practice has been that when council receives it it's also available online to the public so that's the full line item budget on the administrative services website i'm assuming generally where is found thank you very much thank you our next item on the agenda this evening is interim reports of committees of council i think i'm correct in saying we have none of those tonight mr harris is that right thank you we'll now move into our legislative agenda this evening we begin with items for the heritage conservation district
mr harris if you would yes madam president considering the following applications and recommendations from the historical commission for improvements to properties within the heritage conservation district uh sunk yarto holdings llc owner of 250 harrisburg avenue proposes construction of a new elevator tower and a steel carport with an upper level deck on the east elevation of a converted brick warehouse and the second is 201 west king street llc owner owner and Benjamin a Sandburg Arctic architect proposed construction of a new concrete entry steps in a rear rooftop these applications were recommended for approval by the Historical Commission thank you very much mr. Harris we have a
motion on these motion to approve second we have a motion on a second council Craig I'm just confirming your motion is to approve items a B and C is that correct just a and b i'm sorry maybe i'm i'm operating under an older there are two on the uh
two a and b a and b yes thank you very much yeah there's nothing to add more than what is here and motion to approve for both for both okay thank you very much we have a motion
uh and a second for approval of those two items on the agenda this evening are there any uh representatives from the applicants uh here this evening or any members to the public um or i'm sorry any any representatives of the applicants here this evening are there any comments from council from the public on the items
hearing none mr harris mr minn aye mr royale aye mr cleese aye miss craig aye miss diaz aye president vaca
aye next item on our legislative agenda item b these are ordinances for final passage we have administration bill
number seven twenty twenty five mr harris in ordinance of the council of the city of lancaster county of lancaster commonwealth of pennsylvania adopting a five-year capital plan for the fiscal years 2026 to 2030 a program providing for the proper acquisition repair and provision for the necessary equipment and infrastructure for the effective and efficient delivery of public services including projects resulting in the additions replacements or changes to city facilities infrastructure and equipment allowing for a severance provision providing for the repeal of inconsistent ordinances and providing for an effective date motion to approve second we have a
motion and a second council arroyo thank you council president i don't have anything additional add we sat through two hearings with director campbell and director campbell who gave an extensive presentation on the capital budget i just want to extend my gratitude to both director campbell's on providing our first ever capital budget yes thank you very much i've had the
opportunity to meet uh with people about various topics and inevitably it comes up the fact that one of the hallmarks of good government is planning and we are in this rare but amazing position to have a capital budget in front of us and that's not a thing that a lot of cities can say so i'm incredibly proud of that and also want to thank director tina campbell and stephen campbell particularly for their work in putting this together any additional comments
from council counselor i also wanted to thank director tina campbell as well as the department of public works led by director stephen campbell i was very impressed with the planning that went into the capital plan and making sure it had a low budgetary impact for future projections and i look forward to over the next years revisiting it and making sure that we have sound planning and we couldn't have done it without the leadership from both director campbell so i wanted to take
a moment and thank them both thank you counselor med any additional council comments comments from
from the public on the bill hearing none mr. Harris mr. Metz aye mr. Royale aye mr. Cleese aye ms. Craig aye ms. Diaz aye and president vacay aye we have capital
budget yeah that's a big deal if you're a nerd it's a big deal the next the next item yes thank you we got there the next item on our agenda would have been bill six but as i made mention at the top of the meeting that will be introduced at our next regular meeting of council in october so we'll move to item d which is resolutions of which we have won this evening resolution number 63 2025 mr harris a resolution of the
council of the city of lancaster authorizing the filing of the commonwealth finance authority local share account application for funding in the amount not to exceed one million dollars their hdc mid-atlantic's apartments at college avenue three motion to approve
second we have a motion and a second councillor craig thank you council president um the um
local shares account grant comes from the state which are our gaming funds but must come to the municipality and in this case the city is the municipality and then that passes on the funds to the sub grantee and my understanding is that there is someone here from thank you yes tonight we're hearing a presentation from HTC
mid-atlantic counselors you have a copy of this presentations you're able to bring it up in front of you welcome thank you for being here and just yeah
there you go you got it I think I hear it yeah okay thanks good evening my name is Kim Crowder and I have the pleasure of being the senior vice president of real estate development for HDC Mid-Atlantic and so I just want to take a couple minutes to give you a little bit of an update of what we have going on over at College Ave since there's quite a bit of work happening over there and And so if you have your presentation, if you want to flip to the next page, this shows all three phases. Phase one is 64 units and was completed recently, and I'll go into a little bit more detail here. The DELWP wing, which will be phase two, is currently in at PHFA right now for low-income housing tax credits. then what we came to talk about tonight is Marietta phase three which we anticipate would be about 48 units give or take so that's the master plan for what we have going on over at college app so we can skip to the next one thank you so much so this is the building that just opened recently and as I said I'm not going to give you every piece of information here but you know try to give you what I think are the most important pieces and I've been doing this for a long time I've been in affordable housing for over 20 years and and I can tell you that I've never seen this happen before when we opened our door for applications at our offices over on King Street at 8 o'clock in the morning on Saturday April 1st there was a line out the door and down the street for people for applications so within the first 30 days we received over 500 applications for 64 apartments and we were the wait list was closed at the end of April we had so many applications that we wouldn't be able to process them and so I'm very pleased to tell you that by the end of June of this year we were full we have all leased every apartment in the building and we continue to have a three to five year waiting list for those apartments and so I think it just underscores the need in the area and why we're really excited and motivated about doing phase two and then also phase three we can go to the next one now this is just super quick to take you through the apartments if you've driven by on College Ave the outside is lovely all the landscaping is in 64 apartments we have a mix of one and two bedrooms and the rents range from two hundred and twenty eight dollars to nine hundred and fifty dollars per month depending on the unit size and income level and the other thing that I would point out is that something that is really important to HDC is that we don't just provide housing we make sure that we provide resident services on our campuses and so we have resident services on this campus 13 hours a week and that will be available for residents to help connect them to other resources within the community to make sure that they are successful in the apartment and this particular building also has a set-aside for adults with disabilities and so if you come to visit us you'll see that the community is completely accessible and we are really excited that we were able to partner with UDS on phase one okay we can see here's a couple of the community spaces you can see some of these from outside as you're walking by on the left is our community room we were able to I think one of the things that's really interesting about the site is it was a really small site and we were able to fit 64 apartments there and also carve out a little space outside for some of the children that live in the building and so we have this really great playground area that's on the site and kind of protected to it sits kind of in a little courtyard on the campus and so we're really excited about that and then one of the other things that we added is some of these little I call them vignettes these little seating areas for folks to be able to go to if they want to get outside of their apartment and don't really want to go to the full community room and most of these are located outside of the laundry rooms which are located on every floor we can go to the next slide thank you I'm only showing this just so that you get an idea and why it's so important that we are able to partner with the city of Lancaster because it took 20 sources of funds to be able to fund college of one the total development cost was twenty two million eight hundred and seventeen thousand dollars to build those 64 units and you know every dollar that we get in that helps fund one of our projects is absolutely critical and so we're really grateful for the partnership that we had on college of one and would like to see that continued throughout okay we can so college of phase 2 49 apartments it'll be a mix of studio which is a little different for us efficiency one and two bedroom apartments 11 apartments will be set aside for folks who are experiencing or at risk of experiencing homelessness the other thing that is really exciting for us here is that even we're gonna have 49 apartments but we've also partnered with Milagro house and the folks at Milagro house are working with us they're going to take one floor of the Delt building and we'll take the top two and a smidge floors and Milagro House will be providing roughly 19 apartments for single parents who are looking to continue and further their education and so it's you know getting this building up and running is not just the 49 apartments but it's also a larger help to the community by including this wonderful partnership with Milagro House I think that's that's pretty much all you need there and again if we can switch sides again I would just say you know the sources you know every dollar is critical we have a few less sources here but this building is already existing we're not building from scratch and so on we'll be using the delt building it will not be taken down we'll be converting the interior to function for apartments and and residential living but our total development costs at this particular time are nineteen million seven hundred and forty three thousand dollars for phase two and we can we can skip to the next one thank you and this is College Ave phase three this is what is over on Marietta Avenue and so you kind of get a little bit of a look here this one's a little different than what we've been providing and will be a little smaller than the other buildings that we've been looking at in the top right hand corner is where we're looking at where the building would sit and then we're estimating probably summer in the neighborhood of 40 to 50 apartments in that location they would be a mix of one to two bedroom apartments it would additionally be family housing again and we would reserve for all households earning between 20 and 60 percent of the area median income in the Lancaster area and of course just like we would do with phase one and two it would be architecturally compatible with the neighborhood and so this is in early stages of development so things can potentially change but really excited about the opportunity to be able to kind of close this one out and bring all three communities to Lancaster over there on the College Avenue area and we can go to the next one thank you and so here is proposed sources and so this one we're anticipating again a little bit smaller building but we would anticipate the total development cost would be about 19 million dollars so between all three buildings the investment into the community here is you know over 60 million dollars and we're really excited to be able to bring all of that infrastructure and resources and services to the West End neighborhood okay my timeline we can switch to the next one so phase one as I mentioned earlier is complete phase two we submitted our tax credit application to the Pennsylvania Housing Finance Agency in February of this year and we can keep our fingers crossed and hope we're anticipating hearing about awards in October and so really excited about hearing what happens there I did not mention it in the slides but we have a wonderful partnership with LGH and PHFA the Pennsylvania Housing Finance Agency is very excited about that partnership and so we're really excited to be able to work with the group over there we would look to if we get the award then we would be looking to close and begin construction at the end of 2026 that's for phase 2 and be fully leased up and operational in 2028 and so phase 3 which is over on Marietta which we've been talking about we would look to submit an application early in 2027 typically Pennsylvania Housing Finance Agency has applications due q1 and so we would anticipate submitting it then and then before the end of the year hearing about that award there and then fully occupied and leased and functional by the summer of 2030 so just keeping all of the construction and all of the pieces moving to get us to the end of all three phases here and that's basically my presentation I do have a couple pictures if you're interested we did a meet-and-greet with our board of directors if you want to switch to the next slide we did a meet-and-greet with our board of directors and the residents there so everybody got to meet everybody we had pizza we played some get-to-know-you games and it was a really wonderful event and so these are some of the residents and some of our board members at College Ave one and I would like to you know be available if you have any questions do my best to answer them and thank you so much for your
presentation this evening I want to just clarify and I appreciate the back information because I think it's incredible how much goes into these projects yeah and it's worth reiterating again and again like how many funding sources this takes how many people it requires to do this work and how much time it takes to do it for the resolution and the application then that is in front of us this evening this would be for specifically phase three and you showed us sort of like that funding stack for phase three can you tell us how much of that is considered committed at this point so the only thing
that's committed is a contribution that we already have in hand which is from Steinman okay and so we have that and I believe there is a HDC portion and that is also committed those are our first two pieces in and that's why the timeline is yeah that's why it is it takes that long to build the capital stack yes that is correct okay i wanted to make
sure we laid that out very clearly absolutely terrific thank you for your presentation uh i'll take any council comments or questions council craig i just have a comment that um this is
incredible yeah it really is incredible you know to to be here from the beginning when it was a thought and see the whole process follow through um i can't wait to see the whole thing done yeah
it'll be great thank you thank you additional comments from council and i'll just remind before we take uh comments from the public that again these applications are going uh to the state it's not funding that unfortunately the city has but it is state gaming funds that entities can can apply for with municipal support so I'll take any comments on the resolution I'm sorry I did not clarify this fully and there's some other folks coming but to make comment just come right on up to this microphone and that helps us be heard on in the room and both on the recording online so if you'd like to make comment go right on up and please begin with your name and your
block of residence good evening good evening Tony D'Astra 700 block of New Holland Avenue not trying to say anything to freak anybody out it's this is a genuine question I'm hearing that the HUD director Scott Turner might be making a push to kick people out of their housing situations who are in affordable housing programs like the ones offered here just what what can we kind of expect for existing residents who might be undocumented in your facilities I'm looking forward to the project as it is so I don't want to like come at you too much because like you're just one small piece of everything we need to do but do you have any insight to what I'm talking about and what we
might be able to expect so I think I hear two questions is the first question with the changes that are happening at HUD decreased funding at HUD and things like that that we're concerned that people might lose housing is that the first question and then is the second piece about the residents who are actually living there and their status as residents is that the second question
yes I mean I already know that decreases in funding are going to affect the affordable housing opportunities my question is more just if if there are people who are currently in your housing units that are undocumented with these other changes that HUD not funding with more philosophical changes do people need to be concerned about whether they can stay in your units just because I know that you are dependent on funding streams and kind of these odd, in my opinion, unnecessary
decrees. So what I would say first is that the properties that we're talking about here are funded through a program called the Low Income Housing Tax Credit Program. You might see it as LIHTC. And that program basically funds up front. It's a public-private partnership. So we get tax credits from the Pennsylvania Housing Finance Agency and then we sell those tax credits to big investors that put up big money so we actually don't receive a ton of HUD money into these deals they're predominantly paid for through the low-income housing tax credit program and as you look through the capital stack a lot of private foundations and things like that and so I'm not home money is important I want to make sure I say that I think I was quoted in the newspaper the other day with that at home money is incredibly important and critical to our ability to be able to build affordable housing and home money does come trickles down from the HUD budget and so you know we're kind of watching how things are going there but at this particular moment there's nothing that would do that the residents that live there pay their income pay their rent based on their income so there's no no worry about that the other thing I would say is that we have to completely certify our residents before they move in and so all the residents that live there have proven that you know that they're allowed to be here okay thank you any additional
comments from the public good evening Jose Nunez who is 100 block of South
Queen Street I would like to congratulate your program that's
definitely something that as a commissioner and many of the other
commissioners throughout the Commonwealth have advocated for affordable housing so it is great to see that lancaster city and are definitely doing that because that we have definitely we have recognized there's a housing shortage in the commonwealth i mean the commonwealth is growing but when it comes to housing and house opportunity for people who don't have the opportunity to live somewhere it's not there so i do want to congratulate your program i would like to see if i could get a copy or somehow we could connect so maybe we could uh bring a couple of commissioners in and see how we all work together but i think i want to go right jelly program where you definitely definitely hear you say housing shortage and right now i see you're meeting the needs at least in our in our city and in our counties for
people that need that place to live so thank you thank you thank you any further comments
on the public for the resolution good evening hi good afternoon nancy miyan got in court I want to say congratulations to the heart to and to the city and to the administration for all these apartments because it's not a lot but 100 and something apartments that are coming up on that project is amazing and then we are not building nothing new so why are we using the buildings that's amazing guys as well so congratulations on that measurement thank you any further
comments from the public on the resolution hearing none mr. Harris mr.
Menn aye mr. Arroyo aye mr. Cleese aye miss Gregg aye miss Diaz aye and president
Baker aye thank you thank you very much perfect and as my old apparently and new agenda tells us we've reached the end of our legislative agenda this evening which will take us to our second public comment period that comment period is open for items that were not on the agenda. Again, duration of comments is limited to three minutes per speaker. And please begin with your name and block of residence for the meeting record. If anyone wishes to make public comment at this time,
please come to the microphone. Good evening.
Good evening. You know me, I'm Frank or Coleo from old Trinity place. And I'm the one who is appealing the the data center ruling by the zoning officer in back in February calling data center a warehouse you you on the council have requested a process to go through not to cut myself short but but it but in any case you have requested the beginning of a process that i believe is its next step is that you're going to look at a draft ordinance on october 6th that's what i understand but but what i have here for you is something that could shortcut the process which is kind of our idea of what a draft ordinance would be to regulate data centers first thing let me talk about what a data center is a data center is a facility whose Its primary purpose is the centralized storage, processing, management, or dissemination of digital data, information, or applications. This includes, but is not limited to, server forms, cloud computing hubs, co-location centers, and telecommunication switching hubs. Data centers typically house large-scale computer systems and supporting infrastructure such as backup generators, cooling systems, and uninterruptible power supplies. That does not sound like a warehouse to me, I have to say. The uses that we would suggest are conditional uses for both the C3, CM, and SM, all three of those zones. What would be some of the restrictions? Well, going to page three, energy use. Data centers shall operate on 100% renewable energy for all electrical and cooling needs, either through on-site generation or verifiable power purchase agreements. Backup generators should meet or exceed EPA Tier 4 final admission standards, and the facility should not require upgrades to the grid, the municipal electric distribution infrastructure, unless all those upgrades are fully paid for by the applicant. Water and cooling systems, I'll only go over the first provision, all water used for cooling operations or operations shall be non-potable, and all discharges shall be treated to a level equal or better than the affluent standard of the city. Going on to, I'm doing this a little bit out of order, noise emissions should not exceed 50 decibels at any property line, and a period of public informational meeting shall be held. The city may require a community benefits agreement as part of it. And then finally, a decommissioning plan shall outline procedures for the safe removal of server infrastructure, hazardous materials, batteries, electronic waste, all that kind of stuff, backed up by a substantial performance bond in case they decide that the data center glut has gotten a hold and they just wanna throw the keys up on the roof and leave us to clean it up. Those are suggested ordinance capable of Mr. Dastra and others that we would like to be considered as part of the ultimate zoning ordinance amendment for data centers. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Mr. Arcoglio. Are there any additional comments for this period?
Tony Dastra, 700 block of New Holland Avenue. I don't think I need to beat a dead horse. I second what Mr. Arcoglio is saying all about data centers and regulation but two separate things i'll tie it to some of the discussion tonight i am concerned about the soundness of lancaster city government right now i don't know what it is with 2024 but between the tech issues here and agenda posting issues there have been a variety of city government meetings canceled or postponed including yesterday's zoning hearing board which is not good for the productivity of the city especially to any of the developers who may have been there yesterday for whatever decisions but i also recognize those things need to be delayed when sunshine law isn't met because you open a door to reverse decisions so that's a frustration i have but to talk about something separately kind of related to resolution 63 up there the affordable housing situation in lancaster is crazy the housing situation in lancaster is crazy and that project alone is not enough we need to do more not just in terms of construction of units but the regulation of existing units we need rent control in lancaster city for existing units to make sure people can remain in their homes whether that be their apartment building or a house they are renting it is scary for people to have to go to the end of their lease and they're not sure if they're gonna see an increase not because the landlord has invested in their properties but because the other surrounding rents have gotten high on the new units which is pushing up the price of the old units that have no improvements done to them we need practical I'm not out here saying that we should be doing blind rent control policy every single unit just as stuck where it's at but we need reasonable investment to accompany the increases that people experience I think it is time I know it's time for Lancaster City to start having conversation and enacting rent control the people desperately need it and I feel that talk to the priorities of strong neighborhoods safe places sustainable economy because the most dire economic situation is the household and sound government thank you thank you are there
additional comments for this period hearing none we will close the second public comment period i thank everyone uh that will take us to the report of the mayor mayor sirachi i have no additional report this evening thank you thank you uh the next item on our agenda is the report of president of council i don't have anything additional besides again to remind folks to come out to the hispanic heritage festival on october 4th hopefully we'll have lovely weather and not whatever is happening outside right now uh and it'll be a great celebration so thank you are there any uh the next item is council comments are there any council comments this evening hearing none and having reached the end of our agenda i'll hear a motion to adjourn
motion to adjourn second the motion and a second all in favor